Welcome to week six.
6주 차에 잘 오셨어요
Day two a day.
하루 이틀씩요
When we get back into the data, we look back in anger at our data sets, and we build a massive data
데이터로 돌아가면 데이터셋에 분노하며 돌아봅니다 엄청난 양의 데이터셋을 구축해서
set that is going to allow us to move the needle when we get to training.
훈련할 때 진척이 있게 할 거예요 Get it
But first, the majority of today is actually going to be spent talking.
하지만 먼저, 오늘 수업은 대부분 대화를 나눌 거예요
It's going to be a talky, uh, it's going to be a session when we're speaking about strategy, perhaps
전략에 대해 이야기하는 세션이 될 것입니다. 아주 흥미로운 내용은 아닐 것입니다.
not the most gripping stuff, not why you signed up, but it is very important.
왜 등록했는지는 모르겠지만 매우 중요한 내용이죠.
This is good foundational information that is going to ensure that we're approaching what's to come
이건 좋은 기본 정보예요 올바른 방식으로 접근하고 있다는 걸 확실히
in the right way.
해줄 거예요
In particular, I want to talk to you about a strategy for how you go from facing a business problem
특히 전략에 대해 말씀드리고 싶습니다 비즈니스 문제에 직면하는 것에서부터 프로덕션에서
all the way through to an LM solution in production and the steps it takes along that path.
LM 솔루션으로 가는 방법과 그 경로를 따라 진행되는 단계에 대해서요
And I want to tell you that now, because we're about to do it, we're going to go through that exercise
지금 말씀드리고 싶은 건 우리가 그걸 하려고 하기 때문에 그 연습을 통해 진짜 상업적
for our real commercial problem.
문제를 해결할 거라는 거예요
And it's important that you're able to relate to the journey that we go through, because you'll be
우리가 겪는 여정에 공감하는 게 중요해요 여러분도
doing the same thing with your business problems after this.
사업 문제로 똑같이 할 테니까요
I also want to take a moment to compare the three types of technique that we'll be talking about, or
잠시 시간을 내서 우리가 설명할 세 가지 테크닉을 비교해 보죠 모델
that we've talked about for optimizing models.
최적화에 관해선 이미 얘기했죠
I'm talking about whether we're prompting using Rag or using fine tuning.
랙을 사용하든 미세 튜닝을 하든 말이에요
And it's there's a lot of confusion about in what situations do you pick one of those different approaches.
많은 혼란이 있었어요 어떤 상황에서 그런 다양한 접근법 중 하나를 선택해야 하는지에 대해서요
And I want to demystify that and just give you some concrete examples of how you go about deciding what
어떤 기술을 사용할지 어떻게 결정하는지 구체적인 예를 들어 설명해
technique to use.
드릴게요
So first then let me talk about the five step strategy to applying a model to a commercial problem.
그럼 먼저 상업적 문제에 모델을 적용하는 5단계 전략을 말씀드리죠
And the first step is understanding.
첫 단계는 이해예요
This is about really getting deep into the business requirements and understanding what problem are
사업 요구 사항을 깊이 파고들고 어떤 문제를 해결하는지 이해하는 게
you solving?
중요해요
How will you judge success?
성공을 어떻게 판단하죠?
What are the Non-functionals we'll talk about in a second and make sure that that's all carefully documented
비기능적인 건 무엇인지 잠시 후 얘기하고 신중하게 문서화한 준비에
preparation is then about things like testing baseline models and curating your data set and and generally
관한 겁니다 기준 모델 테스트와 데이터 집합 큐레이팅 같은 거죠 앞으로 닥칠 일에 일반적으로
preparing yourself for what is to come.
대비하는 거예요
And what is to come initially is selecting the models, the models that are going to be the either the
가장 먼저 할 일은 모델을 선택하는 겁니다 여러분이 사용할 모델이나
the model you're going to be using, or the handful of models you'll be using as part of the rest of
프로젝트 REST의 일부로 사용할 몇 가지 모델이요
And this is where we'll Thai will draw on a lot of the content from prior weeks.
여기서 타이가 지난 주 내용을 많이 끌어낼 거예요
When we looked at leaderboards and analyzed the pros and cons of different models.
순위표를 보고 여러 모델의 장단점을 분석했죠
Customize is where we use one of the big techniques, like Rag or fine tuning to get more juice out
고객 맞춤화는 래그나 미세 튜닝 같은 중요한 기술을 이용해 모델의 느낌을 더 살리는 작업이에요
of the model, and then productionize something we've not talked about at all, but is hugely important,
그리고 전혀 언급하지 않았지만 매우 중요한 걸 제작하죠 그렇게 모델을
which is then once we've done, we've built and trained our model and it's performing great.
만들고 훈련한 후에 성능이 아주 좋아져요
What comes next?
그다음은요?
Because it's not exactly like the Jupyter notebook that we've been hacking away at is going to end up
우리가 해킹해 온 주피터 노트 같은 게 생산될 것 같지는 않으니까요
Something more has to be done, and that's what we will talk about in a sec.
뭔가 더 해야 합니다 잠시 후 그 얘기를 하죠
Let's start with step one though.
1단계부터 시작하죠
So understanding and this is all common sense.
이해심과 상식의 문제죠
But you know this stuff can't be said enough.
하지만 이런 건 아무리 말해도 모자라요
So just very briefly of course you need to gather the business requirements.
아주 간략하게 비즈니스 요구 사항을 모아야 해요
You need to evaluate.
평가를 해야죠
You need to understand up front how will success be measured.
성공을 어떻게 측정할지 미리 이해해야 해요
Super important.
아주 중요하죠
And we're not just talking about the data science metrics that we know well, but also how will your
우리가 잘 아는 데이터 과학 지표뿐 아니라 여러분의 사용자와 비즈니스
your users and your your business sponsors decide whether the project has achieved its goals?
스폰서는 프로젝트가 목표를 달성했는지 어떻게 결정할까요?
What are the ultimate business metrics that you may not have as immediate influence over, but they
직접적인 영향력은 없지만 이해해야 하는 비즈니스 척도는 무엇일까요?
You need to dig into the data as we've been doing the quantity of it.
우리가 작업한 데이터 양을 살펴봐야 해요
How much?
얼마예요?
What's the DQ, what's the data quality situation like?
DQ가 뭐고 데이터 품질은 어떤지 말이에요
And the format, is it structured, unstructured or a bit of both?
형식은 구조적인가요? 비구조적인가요? 아니면 둘 다인가요?
really make sure that that is deeply understood, because that will affect the model you choose and
깊이 이해하도록 하세요 여러분이 선택한 모델과 그에 접근하는 방식에
how you go about approaching this.
영향을 미치니까요
Determining the non-functional requirements.
비기능적 요구 사항을 결정하는 거죠
Non-functional are stuff like your budget, the how, how much it will need to scale to latency is is
비기능적인 것은 예산 같은 것입니다 얼마나 규모를 키우고 대기 시간을 줄여야 하는지 모델로부터의 응답을
you know how long you can you can wait for each response back from the model if it needs to be a split
얼마나 기다려야 하는지 같은 것입니다 아주 짧은 시간 내에 응답이 와야 하는지를
second response.
알 수 있죠
Um, and also understanding time to market.
시장에 내놓을 시간도 이해해야 하고요
Is there a requirement that this is built in a very short time frame, or is there time to to be working
아주 짧은 시간 안에 만들어야 한다는 조건이 있나요? 아니면 이걸 작업할 시간이 있나요?
on this?
물론 짧은 시간 내에 필요한 것이라면 API를 이용한
a frontier model using an API.
프런티어 모델에 적합하죠
And you know, when it comes to the user interface, something like Gradio is of course allows you to
사용자 인터페이스에 관해서는 그래디오 같은 것이 몇 분 안에
be up and running in a matter of minutes.
실행할 수 있게 해주죠
So this will steer some of your later decisions.
앞으로의 결정에 영향을 줄 거예요
When it comes to preparation, there are really three activities involved.
준비 단계에는 세 가지 활동이 있어요
First of all, you need to research what is already out there, what kind of existing solutions.
먼저, 이미 시중에 나와 있는 게 뭔지 알아야 합니다 현존하는 솔루션이 뭔지요
Solve this problem today and get a very good handle for how well they perform and what they do already.
오늘 이 문제를 해결하고 성능과 현재 하는 일을 잘 파악할 수 있게 될 거예요 get it
As part of that, you should look at at solutions that don't involve data science at all.
그 일환으로 데이터 과학이 전혀 포함되지 않은 솔루션을 찾아보세요
Maybe there's solutions that just have a few if statements in them, and then look at some traditional
if문이 몇 개 있는 솔루션도 있을 수 있고 전통적인 데이터 과학 솔루션도
data science solutions, perhaps like linear regression kind of model.
있을 수 있어요 예를 들면 선형 회귀 모델 같은 거요
If this is something which is trying to predict product prices, say.
제품 가격을 예측하려는 것이라면요
Then that would be a place that you would initially go to.
그럼 처음 가는 곳이 되겠네요
And even if you might say to me, look, I absolutely know, I have no question that an LLM is going
LLM이 이미 있는 것 혹은 기존 모델을 크게 능가할 거라는 데에는
to massively outperform what's already out there or these existing models.
의심의 여지가 없다고 말할 수도 있겠죠
I don't care how they are today.
오늘 상태가 어떻든 상관없어요
The answer would be it's still worth doing this because it gives you a baseline.
대답은 여전히 이렇게 할 가치가 있다는 거죠 기준선을 제공하니까요
It gives you a starting point on which you will improve, and you'll be able to demonstrate the improvement
여러분이 개선할 부분을 표시하는 시작점을 제공하고 새로운 모델에
in a quantified way based on the investment that's made in the new model.
투자한 만큼 퀀트화하여 개선된 점을 보여줄 수 있죠
So even as just a baseline, this is a valuable exercise to do.
기준점만 따져도 좋은 운동이 될 수 있어요
But more than that, you need to know what is already out there.
하지만 그보다 이미 존재하는 걸 알아야 해요
Then comparing the relevant LMS.
그리고 관련 LMS를 비교하죠
First of all, of course you remember we divided this into the basics stuff like the price, the context
먼저, 기억하시겠지만 이걸 기본으로 나눴죠 가격, 컨텍스트 길이
length, the licensing constraints and then the benchmarks.
라이선싱 제약 조건 그리고 벤치마크 같은 거요
Looking on on leaderboards, looking at arenas and understanding if there are specialist scores for
순위표와 경기장을 보면서 이 특정 작업에 대해 어떤 전문적인 점수가
what you're trying to do for this particular task.
있는지 이해하게 되죠
Using things like the seal specialist leaderboards from scale.
물개 전문가의 리더보드 같은 걸 사용해서요
Com that we that we mentioned last time, and of course curating the data, scrubbing it, pre-processing
지난번에 언급했던 컴과 데이터를 큐레이팅하고 스크래핑하고 사전 프로세싱하는 거죠
it.
그리고 아직 특별히 다루지 않은 게 있는데 데이터 집합 분할이에요
Typically you take all of your data and you split it into your training data, and then you reserve
일반적으로 모든 데이터를 트레이닝 데이터로 나누고 모델을 평가할 때 유효성
a chunk for what's called validation when you that you'll be using to evaluate your model, and then
검증을 위해 일부를 예약합니다 그리고 테스트를 위해 마지막
you reserve a final chunk for test.
일부를 예약하죠
And that's something that you hold all the way out so that you can use the validation to be tweaking
끝까지 유지해야 하죠 하이퍼파라미터 수정을 위한 유효성 검증을 사용할
your hyperparameters and getting everything right.
수 있고 모든 게 제대로 되죠
And at the very, very end, you will use the test to gauge the ultimate success of your model.
그리고 마지막에는 이 테스트를 이용해 모델의 궁극적인 성공을 측정하세요
So, uh, cleaning your data, pre-processing it, uh, which is parsing, which is what we've been
데이터를 정리하고 사전 프로세싱하는 건 우리가 해온 파싱이에요
doing, and then ultimately splitting it up is part of preparation.
그리고 궁극적으로 나누는 건 준비 과정의 일부죠
And then select this is something that we've done already, uh, choosing LMS, uh, based on the criteria,
선택은 이미 했던 건데요 기준에 기반해 LMS를 선택하고 실험하고 여러분이
experimenting with them and then training and validating with your curated data.
엄선한 데이터로 훈련하고 유효성을 검사하죠
We haven't done that yet.
아직 안 했어요
That's something that that we are excited to do.
저희도 정말 기대되네요
So I will now pause and we'll continue in the next session with the all important step four to optimize.
이제 잠시 멈추고 다음 시간에 계속하죠 최적화의 중요한 4단계와 함께요